[Music]
Stanford
University what we're going to study
tonight is angular momentum what we're
after is one of the most
important
interesting unintuitive and yet very
very simple aspects of Elementary
particles or anything else for that
matter um they spin they their spin
angular
momentum um let's first talk a little
bit about what angular momentum
is well let me let me pretend for the
moment that you knew what angular
momentum was which you probably
do but uh you you got a rough idea it's
got to do with how fast the system is
rotating and how massive it is and U you
know uh that sort of
thing angular momentum is first of all a
vector quantity it points in a direction
the mathematical definition of the
angular momentum is that its Direction
as a vector points along the axis of
rotation so that's kind of obvious um
there's a rightand rule if the system is
rotating about an axis you don't know
off hand without a definition whether
the angular momentum is pointing that
way or that way all I told you it was
along the axis so you need a rule the
rule is the right- hand rule if it's
rotating that way you wrap your fingers
around the direction of rotation and
your thumb points along the direction of
the angular
momentum that's not something you prove
that's something you define all right
the direction of angular
momentum it's built up out of the mass
and the speed of rotation and that sort
of thing the moment of inertia to be
exact which is a combination of the mass
and the size of the system and the
velocity the angular
velocity and any
system of any
ordinary system composite system this uh
cup here made up out of lots of
atoms it actually can have two kinds of
angular momentum one is called orbital
angular
momentum and the orbital angular
momentum is a consequence of the motion
of its Center of mass it could be
angular momentum angular momentum first
of all is relative to a particular
axis if an object is moving around an
axis it has angular momentum relative to
the axis even if the thing is not itself
not spinning it's a good word spinning
spinning means rotating about some
internal axis it has angular momentum by
virtue of the fact that it's
moving uh let's say in a circular orbit
around my head I see it that has angular
momentum that's not the angular momentum
we're interested in that orbital angular
momentum the angular momentum we're
interested in is the angular momentum of
spin so what is the spin angular
momentum the spin angular momentum is
whatever angular momentum would be there
in a frame of reference where the system
was at
rest so if the system is at rest rest
the only Ang where the center of mass of
the system is at
rest I don't mean that it's not rotating
I mean that its Center of mass is
standing still in the frame of reference
where its momentum is zero ordinary
momentum any leftover angular momentum
is called spin
basically uh
now I wish I had a basketball or
something that I could spin but uh just
to illustrate
ordinarily in ordinary thinking about
things you can take a basketball and you
can start it rotating and you'll say
that's the same thing that's the same
object as the original basketball which
wasn't rotating except it's now
rotating
okay if we also keep track of the fact
that in quantum mechanics the amount of
angular momentum is discreet you can't
interpolate continuously between
different angular
momenta then you could ask the question
it becomes a def question of
definition if you start an object with a
little bit with no angular momentum and
then you rotate it up you spin it up and
give it some angular momentum is it the
same object rotating or is it a new
object now that's obviously a matter of
definition
but in PR practice the real issue is how
much energy does it take to set it into
rotation now you say I can set it into
the smallest amount of rotation
arbitrarily small amount of rotation and
so it takes arbitrarily small amount of
energy to start rotating but that's true
in classical mechanics you have a
continuous interpolation between the
thing not rotating and the thing Ro
ating but in quantum mechanics you don't
have a continuous
interpolation and so I would say it's a
matter of definition whether you want to
think of a rotating nucleus as the same
object or a discretly different object
but the real question as I said is how
much energy does it take to start a
system in
rotation given that the rotational
states are discrete
it makes sense how much to ask how much
energy does it take to set it into the
first excited state the first lowest
amount of rotation that you can get if
it's very small it only takes a little
bit of
energy then the object is probably
pretty recognizable as the same object
as when it was rest but if it takes an
enormous amount of energy well it could
take so much amount so much energy that
it would just blow the system apart so
so for example
uh an
atom if
uh you try to set an atom into rotation
with too much angular momentum the
electrons will just fly off and that
atom won't even be there so you
certainly make things which are
distinguishably
different when you set them into
rotation and and discreetly
different what about an
electron can you set an electron forget
for the moment that the electron has
intrinsic spin for a minute let's forget
that for a minute can you set an
electron into
rotation so that it resembles the same
object except rotating about some
Axis or is the electron somehow so small
and so pointlike that it doesn't make
any sense to set it into rotation a
thing which is infinitely small a simple
point a simple mathematical point it's
hard to conceive of at least with our
usual mental pictures of setting that
thing into
rotation but we don't know that the
electron is infinitely small maybe the
electron is not infinitely
small uh if it's not infinitely small
maybe we have a chance of seeing a
rotating
electron so the question becomes how
much energy does it take to to set an
electron into
rotation now uh the answer tends to
depend on the size of an object for a
given Mass it depends on the size of an
object surprisingly maybe it's
surprising maybe it's not surprising the
smaller the object the more energy it
takes to set it into
rotation big objects you can set into
very very small uh angular
velocities small objects
take larger amounts of energy to excite
them to a given amount of rotation to a
given amount of angular
momentum the electron may be so small
and it probably it's known to be so
small that the energy that it would take
to give it one more unit of angular
momentum would be astronomical would be
uh maybe the plunk energy or some
humongously large
energy and so we don't see in the
laboratory rotating
electrons in fact the rotating electron
may be so different from an ordinary
electron that we wouldn't even call it
an electron
anymore
uh the upshot of this is that when we
talk about objects in Quant mechanics we
are or particles in particular or nuclei
or any simple systems relatively simple
systems they have a amount of angular
momentum which characterizes them and
which once and for all is fixed you
don't talk
about electrons with different angular
different spin angular momentum the
angular momentum of the electron is
always the same if it has any angular
momentum at
all you say why is that well just
because if it had more angular momentum
you'd call it a different
object now angular momentum as I said is
a vector we're going to Define exactly
what what uh how to define it at a
moment but it's a vector it has a
length the length of the vector is
proportional to the speed of rotation
and so
forth it can point in any
direction or at least classically it can
point in any direction shall we think of
pointing the angular momentum of an
object in different directions as
corresponding to different objects let's
suppose we now do have an object which
has some angular
momentum we call it what should we call
it I don't want to call it an electron
it's
a
um a what
spon spinon spinon okay a spinon it's a
spinon we identify it as a spinon and
its angular momentum is pointing that
way can the angular momentum point in
another Direction well yes it better be
able to because the laws of physics are
rotationally invariant there's nothing
special about one a AIS than another
axis so yes the same object can be made
to rotate in a different direction even
if it can't be made to rotate with more
total angular momentum so pointing it in
different directions we would say
corresponds to the same object if an
electron does have angular momentum we
should be able to think of that angular
momentum in any direction on the other
hand the amount of angular momentum the
magnitude of it is
quantized and so as I
said uh the Gap to the first excited
state of the electron may be so large
that we wouldn't even call it an
electron okay so the angular momentum
can point in any
direction it is
quantized and now we have to enter into
the theory of angular momentum tonight
what we're going to do is the
mathematics of angular momentum and it's
very magical it's magical and it seems
totally abstract
ra
um totally
unintuitive and then pump out comes
experimental uh facts and
predictions and uh the entire
properties
of spin as an experimental um you know
observational fact about particles all
right let's Yeah question touch on why
the energy required to spin small
particle
okay do you know what do you know what
the moment of inertia of an object
is
okay let me answer the question uh the
simplest it is counterintuitive a little
bit well it isn't it
isn't um the moment of inertia is a
combination of the
um the mass of the
object and the radius of the object we
take a ball of some sort all right it's
Mr
squared now it depends on the detailed
shape of the object and it depends on
how the matter is distributed sometimes
it's three three Hales Mr s you know but
it's of order Mr s and it's called the
moment of inertia I okay the energy of a
rotating
object that's one thing now then there
is the angular momentum the Ang momentum
of the object is made up if the object
let's say the outer boundary of the
object let's say is moving with velocity
V right
then roughly speaking order of magnitude
the mass times the velocity that's the
ordinary momentum of a of a piece of it
mass times velocity and if you multiply
that by R that's uh that's the angular
momentum
momentum times distance is angular
momentum so the momentum of a of a
little piece of it times the distance
from the center of it is the angular
momentum and if you write down the
kinetic energy the kinetic energy is 1
12 mv^ squared what you'll discover is
that it's the angular momentum squared
divided by the moment of inertia twice
the moment of inertia to be
exact so that's the energy the kinetic
energy of
rotation is the angular momentum squar
divided by twice the moment of inertia
now for a given Mass let's say the mass
of the electron the smaller it is the
smaller the moment of inertia but the
moment of inertia goes in the
denominator and that means the amount of
energy that it takes to increase the
angular momentum by one unit is
inversely proportional to the square of
the size of the object okay so it's a
classical mechanical fact the only thing
that comes new in quantum mechanics is
that the angular momenta is discret are
discret but the fact that for a given
angular momentum a smaller object cost
more energy that's a classical
mechanical
fact okay let's uh let's do some of the
mathematics and tonight we're really
going to do the mathematics of angular
momentum it's both totally
unintuitive and
simple right simple enough uh and this
is a great example of where you see
extremely abstract mathematics which you
can follow suddenly popping out uh uh
very unintuitive answers but
nevertheless experimental
answers all right let's uh let's
begin well first of all let's begin in
with a single particle orbiting a
center circular orbit for
Simplicity the angular momentum is the
momentum of the particle times the
distance from the origin mass time
velocity times distance but we'll just
call it
momentum that's the angular momentum in
this very simple
context uh is it positive or is it
negative that depends on the sense of
rotation going this way
I think I call positive going that way
I'll call negative but uh it's not very
important that's the angular
momentum uh of a point object now this
object has momentum has angular momentum
because it has momentum and it has
momentum because it has velocity so this
is not yet spin but now supposing we had
two
particles at opposite ends of the
diameter here both going with the same
sense of rotation now the center of mass
would be at rest the center of mass of
the system would be at rest but the
angular momentum would certainly not be
zero it would be the sum of the two
angular momenta and they're going in the
same direction so here's an example
where the center of Masset of the system
can be at rest but there's still angular
momentum this is
spin
okay all right now let's uh get a little
more refined in our precise definition
of angular momentum I said before
angular momentum is a
vector and that means or that's denoted
by putting a little arrow over the top
of it momentum is a
vector and also spatial
location here's the spatial location of
an
object it is relative to an origin
relative to an origin we can call it a
vector it's the radial vector
let's talk about the components first
before we get on to what angular
momentum is the components of the r
Vector are just the coordinates of the
position of the particle so the
components of R this R over
here let's write it over here the
components of R are just X Y and
Z X Y and Z being the coordinates of the
position of the particle and I'm also
going to sometimes call
them X1 X2 and
X3 X3 being Z X2 being y X1 being
X okay so we have these two vectors and
somehow the angular momentum is a
product of the two vectors the angular
momentum is itself a vector how do you
make a vector out of two vectors by
multip by multiplication what kind of
rule of multip multiplication is there
that takes two vectors and um combines
them together by some rule of
multiplication to make a new vector and
there only that's right there's only one
rule there's only one such
rule uh and that's the cross product the
cross product R and in fact there's an
ambiguity is it R cross P or P cross R
that's a question of whether you're
right-handed or left-handed do you use
the right-hand rule or the left-hand
rule uh the standard convention
is that it's R cross
P that
right I don't
remember uh I think it's right-handed
maybe it's left-handed I'm not sure I
don't
remember uh we we could figure it out
but I don't want to yeah uh it's our
cross
P oh we labeled the coordinates of the r
Vector there's also the P Vector the p
Vector also has coordinates and its
coordinates are PX py and
pz
or P1 P2
P3 okay those that's that's the notation
we'll use now I can ask what are the
components of the angular momentum so
for that all you have to know is how to
build a cross product and I'll assume
everybody knows that to build a cross
product so let's just do it here's the
rule the X component of the cross
product the X component of the angular
momentum is the Y component of position
times the Z component of
momentum
minus the Z component of position times
the Y component of
momentum this is the only one that I
ever remember LX equals y time pz all
right I read that off the other one here
I know that I have to put them in the
opp I have to change pz to Z py to Y and
then I want to go down from there LX l y
and
LZ I never remember them but I know the
rule the rule is you just cycle from X
to Y to Z and back to X to Y to Z think
of X Y and Z as being a points on a
clock and you go from one to the next so
when you go from X to y y goes to z z
goes to
X let's go down to the next one y z x
this is not I'm not finished with the
formula z x y
py
minus
xpz
minus uh y
PX the only reason I emphasize the
cycling is to keep track of the sign how
do I know that l y isn't xpz minus Z PX
okay that's the rule you cycle through
that
way and
um
right that's the component of angular
momentum of a point
particle moving in the vicinity of some
origin of coordinates right it's the
orbital angular momentum of that
particle is not the spin angular
momentum to make a spin angular momentum
for system of ordinary In classical
mechanics to make a spin angular
momentum you've got to have a lot of
particles at least two anyway I showed
you how to make a spin angular momentum
with two of them you have to have
several particles two being a POS
several all right how do you build the
angular momentum or composite system you
just add the angular momenta as vectors
you add them as vectors you add the
angular momentum of all the
constituents once you add the angular
momentum then you can have a spin where
the total momentum is equal to zero but
the angular momentum is not equal to
zero but this is the basic formula for a
single indivisible Point particle so and
as I said you just add them up for uh
for a lot of
particles next step we want to do the
quantum mechanics of angular momentum
this is the classical mechanics actually
it's also the quantum mechanics but to
get to the quantum
mechanics the basic mathematics of
quantum mechanics is the quantum
mechanics of operators
all quantities of physical significance
meaning to say things that you can
observe measure all those things are
represented in quantum mechanics by
what operators yeah Mission operators
operators and there's no
special exception about angular momenta
the components of angular momenta are
are represented by operators but to
figure out what those operators are all
we really need to know is what the
operators which represent uh uh position
and momentum are in fact we don't even
really have to know very much
about
the detailed property of the position
and the momentum operation
all we have to know is their commutation
relations with their commutation
relations that's all we need to know in
order to carry on and work out
everything okay so what what does it
mean or what are the
implications of two operators commuting
let's suppose I have two operators which
represent two observable
quantities the aess and the Bess of a
system and I know that A and B commute
what does that tell me about uh
observation yeah exactly you can
simultaneously measure them what if they
don't
commute then you can't simultaneously
measure
them the most famous example of two
things that you cannot simultaneously
measure of course is position and
momentum the implication is that in
quantum mechanics The Operators
representing where I erase them P1 P2
and P3 on the one hand X1 X2 and
X3 don't commute among
themselves okay so what are the right
commutation relations all right now to
some extent these are postulates of
quantum mechanics you find them in the
first chapter of D's book and they're
basically uh postulates if you like uh
but uh there there are limitations on
what you can write down but we're going
to take them as postulates
all right the first postulate is that
you can simultaneously measure all three
coordinates of position there's no
limitation on how well you can determine
the X Y and Z coordinates of position
they're all simultaneously measurable
and the implication of that is that
every x commutes with every every other
X we can write that down x i
XJ equal 0 for all I and J for all I inj
incidentally anything commutes with
itself it' be very weird if something
didn't commute with itself that would
say you could measure it but you
couldn't measure it simultaneously with
itself bad idea okay so everything
commutes with itself same thing for
momenta there is no limitation on being
able to simultaneously measure the
different components of
momentum
so p
I
PJ equals
zero what about X's with PS well that's
exactly what the uncertainty principle
is about it tells us that we cannot
simultaneously measure coordinates and
position but which coordinates and which
positions can which components can we
not measure simultaneously and the
answer there's not a lot of freedom
about this but uh nevertheless I'm going
to just state it as a poate that X1 and
P2 can be simultaneously measured the x
coordinate of a particle and the Y
component of its momentum are not
limited by the uncertainty principle
it's the X component of position and the
X component of momentum which are not
simultaneously
measurable so we have that x
with
PX is not equal to zero anybody remember
what it is equal to
IH bar it's small why because uh
certainly don't expect macroscopic big
heavy objects toh to
behave uh with such bizarre behaviors so
it's small one unit of angular momentum
sorry one unit of plunks
constant uh and so forth for Y and
Z and so we can write down a general
formula that the commutator of
XI with
PJ is I bar if I equals J and zero if I
doesn't equal J is that clear okay so to
represent that we put the chronica Delta
here and that's a nice uh systematic way
to describe the properties of position
and momentum that turns out all to be
all we really need to
know uh in order
to in order to understand the properties
of angular momentum in order to
understand the properties of spin let's
see there's one other point uh that is
worth
emphasizing and that's that angular
momentum has units of plunks constant
how do I know that well angular momentum
has units of distance time
momentum uh here's distance time
momentum on the right hand side is plunk
constant it also occurs of course in the
uncertainty principle Delta X Delta p is
greater than or equal to whatever uh
some number times Plank's
constant so you see that Plank's
constant has units of length time
momentum and angular momentum has units
of length time momentum so it's not
completely surprising that angular
momentum is quantized in units of plunks
constant
uh in units of the basic Quantum in
nature which is plunk
Conant okay but uh we we haven't gotten
it yet I just pointed that
out what I want to work out for you is
the commutation relations of the
components of angular momentum we're
going to find out that once we work out
the commutation relations of the angular
moment components of the angular
momentum we can forget
this we won't need it anymore it's just
the components of the angular momentum
whose commutation relations we want all
right so let's do it over
here let's first compute the commutator
of LX with
ly okay it's not very hard uh I will
have to wing it a little bit because uh
I haven't uh I would have to remind you
what all the rules about the algebraic
rules of commutators are but it's pretty
simple it's simple enough that uh that
you can see what happens all right so we
want the commutator of LX with l
y LX with l y is ypz is the
commutator of
ypz minus
zpy that's the
first uh entry into the commutator and
we're going to commute that
with that was that was LX with ly which
is
zpx minus xpz
I think in the last 24 hours I've done
this three times on the
Blackboard first uh the first two times
of last night when the 30 people who
failed the course showed up
late you know it's there's another cheat
that you didn't you didn't use you use
the cycling from top to bottom yeah but
you can actually just cycle from left to
right and forget about the other two
equations so Y starts with z z starts
with X all
right however you like yeah yeah that's
fine
right okay let's see if we can figure
this
out let's see
ypz let's look at the commutator of this
term of the first factor with this
term of the second
Factor there's nothing to
prevent why you know when you think
about commutators you're thinking about
pushing operators through each other can
they freely pass through each other
without a change in the uh in the value
of the operator all right now y commutes
with X so it can go right past X it also
comput commutes with
pz pz commutes with X and pz commutes
with pz so you can push this one right
through this one no obstruction
so these two commute with each other
contribute nothing to the
commutator I think there's another
combination let's see is it this one Z
yeah these two yeah these two also
commute with each other the two which
don't commute with each other or two
pairs this and this and this with
this so let's see if we can work it
out um we have y pz z p X the only thing
which doesn't commute here is pz with
Z right so I maintain that the answer is
just y * I don't want to use
red is just y *
PX and it doesn't matter which order you
write them down y * PX and then there's
the commutator of pz with Z what's the
commutator of pz with
z
minus IH bar why is it minus IH bar
because commutators in the opposite
order change sign commutator is
anti-symmetric meaning when you change
the order of what you write in the
bracket it changes
sign AB minus ba if if you interchange B
it would just change sign all right so
this this commutator of pz with Z is
minus I
bar all right then we have this guy over
here with this one over
here what is it that doesn't commute
here py and X
commute so there a plusus * minus is
plus uh py * X but then we have the
commutator of Z with pz and that's I bar
so I bar other IH bar or in other words
the whole thing oh that's sorry uh what
did I
write do this
one
um piece of Y right X piece X piece of
Y and again in each of these Expressions
here it doesn't matter which way you
order the two uh constituent operators
here okay the whole thing then is I
bar xpy y -
ypx whole bunch of mumbo jumbo but uh
nevertheless It's very effective xpy -
ypx
is
LZ so we've learned that the commutator
of LX with l y is just sorry IH
bar I bar
LZ that's kind of pretty that when you
commute to components of the angular
momentum you get back another component
of angular momentum you don't have to
remember anything about P's and X's
anymore the commutation relations of
angular momenta are closed among
themselves and the algebra call this the
algebra of angular momentum is something
abstract which doesn't even really
remember where it came from meaning to
say that it doesn't contain the PS and
X's
anymore that's LX with l
y then either cycling vertically or
horizontally doesn't matter you can
write down the next
one l y with
LZ is I bar
LX and that's the next one XY
Z
yzx is I HR l z l l
y okay those are those are the
fundamental um
relationships on which the theory of
angular momentum is built now the next
fact which I will tell you is that if
you have many particles and you add up
the angular
momenta and then them you find exactly
the same relationship it doesn't matter
that this was a single particle could be
many particles and it could be many
particles in their own rest frame in the
rest frame of the center of mass so this
would also be the commutation relations
for the components of spin angular
momentum so these as I said are our
starting
point uh you might ask is there anything
special about the choice of axes chose
the X the Y and the Z Z axis but I never
told you what X and Y and Z were they
could be the uh the edges of the room or
they could be as you want it to use a
diagonal uh Direction and two other
funny diagonal directions as long as
they're mutually perpendicular they form
a perfectly good cartisian coordinate
system given the components of a vector
in one frame of reference you can
commute compute them in any other frame
of reference so in principle we could
work out from is the commutation
relations of the components of angular
momentum in some other set of
axes what we would find is that they
have exactly the same
form they would have exactly the same
form if I chose Prime backis axes which
are different I would just put some
primes in
here in other words the commutation
relations of angular momentum are
rotationally invariant they take the
same form in every frame of reference
and that guar guarantees that whatever
Theory we're making of angular momentum
it'll it will be independent the the
observable facts will be independent of
what axes we choose to uh to do the
mathematics
here is it independent of translation as
well it is but uh it is it is but uh the
spin the spin Ang the spin angular
momentum is um but certainly this much
is quite independent of
yeah right but it's also yes it is also
independent of
translation okay next step now we're
going to be now we're going to be doing
the abstract algebra okay
magic uh un likee what we did so far
well so far so
far we didn't get anything out it only
becomes magic when you get something all
right you can you know you can write
down infinite number of formulas you
could get a computer you can plug in
these rules into a computer and then
have it grind out all possible
theorems
uh uh ape can do that right and mostly
they'll grind out uninteresting theorems
it becomes magic when all of a sudden
you look back and you say wow that's an
experimental fact that I can um
confirm or that's telling me something
interesting about the physics of uh the
operational um process of
measurement so we'll get there but we're
still just doing abstract mathematics
for the moment of course I know where
I'm going you don't know where I'm going
so you just have to follow but after you
see it you'll know and then you can do
it
yourself okay so
uh some of you
know the X Y and Z axis that you choose
are spinning along with the particle no
that's that we don't want to do that we
don't want to do we want to use inertial
reference frames and spinning reference
frames are not inertial nevertheless I
will tell you it's still true but uh but
we don't want to get into that at a
moment certainly the angular momentum is
not invariant undergoing the rotating
frames of reference if we had a system
which is spinning and it had some Spin
and we went to a rotating frame of
reference which spin with it then it
wouldn't look like it had any angular
momentum so it's clear that uh that we
don't want to go to rotating frames of
reference or at least the angular
momentum won't be in
variant so inertial frames of reference
reference frames which uh have no
centrifugal forces and no coriolis
forces and so
forth all right now we're going to
invent two new operators which are very
simply related to these simple as
possible
they're called L plus and minus are two
of
them let's write them down l+ and L
minus l+ is equal the LX + i l
y and L minus is equal to
lx- i l
y I'll tell you right now what these are
these are raising and lowering operators
analogous to the harmonic oscillation
the creation and Annihilation
operators they take an angular momentum
along a given axis namely the z-axis and
they bump you up a step and they bump
you down a step but we're going to show
that we're going to show that another
definition is that the measurable values
of LZ we're going to be concentrating on
LZ now there's nothing special about the
z-axis but on the other hand there's
nothing nothing to forbid me from
focusing on the
z-axis nothing special about it
nevertheless I wish to choose an axis uh
to uh to work with I'm going to choose
the z-axis and I'm going to call the IG
values of LZ the measurable values that
I can take on I'm going to call them
M *
H H bar is just a number if we set H bar
equal to one which I think I will do now
because I will never Blackboard in real
time be able to keep track of all the H
bars later on we can put them
back LZ is just called M that's a
historical
notation M as I said is the angular
momentum in units of har bar okay so
it's uh but um and it'll turn out to be
a quantized
variable okay it's called M historical
reasons that I don't know and uh that's
a notation we
use what I want to calculate I'm not
interested for our purposes in the
commutator between LX l+ and L minus
I'll tell you if you want to work it out
it's proportional to
LZ but don't that's not our interest
right now I want to work out the
commutator of
l+ with
LZ you'll see why as we go
along right so we want L plus with LZ
also L minus with LZ but let's do L plus
with LZ so this is equal to commutator
of LX + i y with LZ well we have all the
rules this is easy oh my God what going
I do with them here they are all right
commutator of LX with LZ can somebody
read it off for
meus l y i l Yus i l y we're setting H
bar equal to one for the moment right so
LX with LZ do I believe you mhm I do
minus i l
y and what
about uh what
about l y with LZ so then there plus
I and
now l y with LZ somebody read it off
IX I LX so it's i^2 LX and i^2 is just
[Music]
-1 and this is just equal to
minus
l+ all right it's minus LX Plus i
y okay so we have our first commutation
relation I think I can get rid of this
it's just minus
[Applause]
l+ what about L minus with l
z I won't drag you through it I'll just
write down the answer I think the answer
is plus L minus when you compute when
you commute l+ with LZ you get back l+
when you compute when you commute L
minus with LZ you get back L minus with
a sign that uh that depends on whether
it's l Plus or L
minus these are the basic commutation
relations that we're going to
use okay the next step is I want to
show that l+ and L minus are bumping
operators which bump you up and down
like raising or like creation and
Annihilation
operators for harmonic oscillators that
when L plus and L minus a they change
the Z component of angular momentum
we're going to focus remember we can
only measure one component of the
angular momentum at a time oh I didn't
say that did I no we didn't say that we
should say it right now how many of the
components of angular momentum can we
simultaneously measure answer is one
any two of them don't
commute any two of them don't commute
and so at most we can measure one
component of angular momentum at a we
pick one direction we call it the
quantization axis but there's nothing
special about it and we focus on
it and uh we are interested now in the
possible
values that LZ can take on in other
words what are the possible values of M
and what we're going to do now is we're
going to show that l+ bumps you up in M
increases the Aon value M by one unit so
let's see if we can do
that let's suppose we have a
state let's call it
m such that
LZ acting on M is equal to what m m
on in other words that little m is an
igen value of Z with igen vector k
Vector
M that's what it means to say that n is
an I value and that's that's we know
what that means been through this a
number of
times what we want to
prove is that if you act with l+ on M
that's a new
Vector let's put a red box around
it
it's a new it's a new C Vector what I
want to prove is that that's a cat
Vector with I can value M
+1 with I value of
LZ equal to m+ one so let's do it all we
have to do is multiply this by LZ and
see what we
get what should we get if it really is
an i
Vector get some we should get n +1 * the
same thing in the red box we should get
I won't bother writing it down but uh we
should get n +1 * the thing in the red
box all right now this would be easy to
compute if l+ if
LZ commuted with l+ then we would just
push the LZ through and use the fact
that LZ on M just gives us M *
n okay that would be easy but it's not
that easy we we can't push LZ through l+
why because they don't commute but if we
use the commutation relations we can so
let's write out what this commutation
relation means it means l+
LZ minus LZ
l+ equals - l+ I just written it out by
hand in excruciating detail the thing
that I'm interested in here thing that
came up here was LZ *
l+ so let's put that on one side of the
equation and write that this is l+
LZ plus
l+ oops not LZ but
l+ equals LZ
l+ that's what I want LZ l+ with LZ on
the left l+ on the right okay and here I
have it on the left side of the equation
we'll see is it useful we're going to
find out if is useful so this is equal
then
to L plus
LZ acting on
M plus l+ acting on
N I'll stop here if there are any
questions I think I've been clear but if
not
I'll okay but now it's
easy what is LZ when it acts on M M just
replaces the LZ by an M right so let's
take an M out put the M over
here take out this
LZ close it up a little bit and *
l+ and here we just have l+ * m what are
we going to do with that I don't know
what we're going to do with it but we
just uh put we're going to do with this
put a red box around
it l+ * m l+ *
m same Red Box same thing in the red box
on each side so what's in the red box
has the property that L when LZ hits
[Applause]
it it multiplies it by m +
1 thing in the red box is an igen Vector
of
LZ with IG value m +
1 that's a little bit of magic and what
it tells us is that if we have a state
with a given value of
LZ there must be another state with one
additional
unit of LZ in other words you can bump
up LZ by one
unit
um you can bump down
LZ the same way except using the
lowering operator so you can check that
that L minus on M gives you an igen
Vector with igen value M minus
one right so now let's think about now
we've learned something rather
non-trivial we've discovered that the
spectrum of angular momentum Z component
of angular
momentum is spaced by in
here's the spectrum of angular
momentum and whatever it is it's spaced
by
integers I don't know it could be uh I
don't know what spectrum of angular
momentum is yet respect to the possible
values of it it could be pi < + 1 < + 2
< + 3 < - 1 < - 2 or it could be the <
TK 2 2 + 1 2 + 2 whatever they are
they're gapped by integers but we still
don't know what the uh what any one of
them is know it's
only
uh yeah we we we'll come to that we'll
come to
that
okay now next question can it go on and
on forever now remember we're talking
about a particular particle we're
talking about a particle of some
kind we're not talking about um the
whole world we're just talking about
some particular elementary particle
let's say a neutron or even a
nucleus how much can we bump up the
angular momentum the Z component of
angular momentum before it's not the
same object anymore before we simply run
out of possibilities so we're talking
about an object let's think classically
for a
minute it's rotating about some
axis and we're not allowed to increase
the rate of rotation that would give us
a new object a different
object uh but we are allowed to rotate
the angular
momentum we're allowed to rotate the
angular momentum but we're not allowed
to increase it its amount without
changing the whole nature of the
object
okay so there's another another way of
saying it is that there's a given length
or given value of l s the magnitude of L
is fixed the magnitude of L is fixed and
it characterizes the
particle just as a particle is
characterized by mass it's also
characterized by a length of the angular
momentum vector or better yet the square
of the length of the angular momentum
Vector okay how do we maximize the Z
component of angular
momentum we simply point it we simply
point the object upward we point the
spin axis upward and that's going to be
the maximum angular momentum the maximal
Z component of the angular momentum so
from an intuitive point of view there
ought to be a maximum value for the
angular momentum of a specific
particle a CPUs and after that
nothing well how can that be how can
that be we've already proved that by
acting with
l+ we bump up the angular momentum how
can there possibly be a ceiling to the
uh to the
rule the answer is exactly the same as
the harmonic oscillated creation and
Annihilation operators remember what
what happens to the annihilation
operator if you hit the bottom State the
state of lowest
energy it just gives you
zero okay that's the one possibility we
left out here that perhaps there are
states or a state where l+ will give
zero that would have to be the case if
there was a maximum angular
momentum
so for the maximum angular momentum if
there is such a thing and there is for
every given
object
l+ on let's call M
Max must equal
zero so there's a cut off you can't go
past a certain
point what about the minimum value of
the angular
momentum minimum means the one deepest
down the C
it had better just
be the negative of this why must it be
the negative why couldn't it be
something else that's just rotational
invariance if you can build a system
with an angular momentum along a given
axis of a certain value you must be able
by by rotational invariance by every
axis being equivalent to every other
axis you must be able to rotate that
angular momentum and have exactly the
same value except pointing in the
opposite
direction
so the
bottom must be that's call M Max and M
Min must be equal to minus M Max = M Min
m Min of course being
negative and from M Max and M
Min we can bump up an integer or bump
down an integer and then that now fixes
for us some properties of the spectrum
um it's got to be symmetrically located
relative to zero and it's got to be
gapped or spaced by integers there's
only two possibilities if you think
about it for a few minutes there's only
two possibilities well there's many
possibilities but they come in two
families the first in the first family
zero is a possible value
of M this is M =
0 and then m = 1 m =
one and so forth until you get the M Max
and until you get the M
Min m
Max M
Max - M
Max how many such states are they all
together yeah 2 m Max +
[Applause]
1 M Max here M Max here and then one
more at the origin twice mx + 1 that's
the number of possible
States cuz I haven't told you what M Max
is but that's because MX could be
anything depending on the specific
particle or the specific object we're
talking about
so specific
particles have their own value of M Max
and that Ma Max is called the spin of
the particle for example there are
particles that have no spin at all then
the spectrum of angular momentum is just
m equals 0 and nothing
else when you hit it with a raising
operator you get zero when you hit it
with a lowering operator you get zero
that's spin
zero then there's the possibility of
spin one spin one is a situation where n
=
1 is the ceiling and M = minus1 is the
floor can't go below the floor can't go
above the ceiling that's spin one called
the spin one
particle you can have spin two particles
you can have spin three particles and so
forth uh an example the Hig boson to
spin zero
particle the photons to spin one
particle and zebon is a spin one
particle are there spin two particles in
nature well the graviton is a spin two
particles how about spin three
particles no object that is ordinarily
called an elementary particle is spin
three but there are certainly objects
with spin three there are nuclei with
spin three uh there are basketballs with
spin three uh there are galaxies who
spin three rather hard to find them but
uh yeah there are lots of objects with
spin three but among the elementary
particles in nature the things that we
ordinarily call the elementary particles
spin zero spin one and spin two spin two
is a now that's not completely clear
because I missed a a
possibility and the possibility was that
Nal 0 was not in the
Spectrum the only other
situation which is symmetrical about the
vertical and which is gapped by integers
spaced by integers let's put zero over
here is to start at n = a
half and M = minus a half and then go
upward in units of one so this one would
be 3 halves this one will be minus
3es and so forth until you come to M Max
in this case all the all the values
would be half
integers the simplest
example being just the half spin
particle again you call you you the you
um describe the particle as having a
spin equal to the maximum value okay so
an object which only had spin a half or
Z component equal to a half and minus a
half that's the simplest object with the
half spin kind of
Spectrum that's called a half spin
particle the next one would be called a
spin three Hales particle and spin five
Hales particle and particles come in
these two types integer Spin and half
integer spin the question no half half
Spin and integer spin yeah is there a
maximum half spin
for yeah yeah but the only thing is that
that the maximum is going to be a half
integer it's going to be not an integer
spin three Hales particle a maximum
would be three halves spin five Hales
particle spin
maximum yeah oh yeah uh in
all uh speculations about elementary
particles basically the combination of
lenen variant quantum mechanics and a
few things other things things tell you
that there are no particles Elementary
particles to spin higher than two that
will allow zero one and two and it will
allow a half and three Hales so all the
standard particles of Elementary
partical physics are zero a half one
three halves and two but you can build
composite objects yeah the your line
there allows for negative spin values
well uh negative spin value just means
just just means rotated around the axis
so it's pointing down and we
characterize the particle by the maximum
value of the spin meaning the maximum
positive value so let me go kind a way
off topic here so why why are there only
say two
orientations who said there were two
there been zero particle or none okay
two or there's been three particle there
are
three I know what you're asking you're
asking what happens to the directions in
between you're asking yeah okay we're
going to talk about
that that's where Quantum that's quantum
mechanics in your
face let me add one to that yeah we
we'll come to that that's not off topic
at all okay let me ask one more let me
add to that when we get to that topic
which is what about like cork screw
wav cork screw a cork screw motion is a
motion which is moving and rot rting a
wave
is an electromagnetic wave can be a
corkscrew wave yeah meaning circular
polarization circularly polarized waves
yes currently all our waves all our map
very classical W yeah yeah yeah but
nevertheless a circularly polarized
photon is one with a spin angular
momentum along the axis going in exactly
the direction that you think a
circularly polarized wave
is composed of circularly polarized
photons and a circularly polarized
Photon means one whose angular momentum
along that axis is pointing along that
axis but to talk about to talk about
objects at rest which is what we're
talking about now it doesn't make sense
to talk about cork screw motion because
cork screw really has to do with a
simultaneous rotation and motion along
an axis so at the moment the the object
you're hunting for the mathematical term
is
helicity helicity is got to do with the
um orientation of the spin relative to
the direction of
motion but we'll we'll uh we'll come to
that very very important is there an
elementary particle that we know of that
has three halves
spin
uh depends on whether defying the term
no know electon we measured or that we
have hes I guess
um it's a matter of speculation
speculation is too uh too um wrong word
conjecture it's a matter of conjecture
that there
exists a super symmetric part partner of
the graviton which is called the
gravitino which has beenin great ha that
has not and will never be EXP
experimentally
detected claim if you use I have a
question the directly detected
directly at this
point the L's are no longer acting like
the their original definition because if
you just plug their or their original
definition
in you wouldn't get these limits so
there must be a difference well it looks
like there's no longer acting on the
original space of the S functions that
we had somehow there's a new s functions
um the new the original space of cats no
this it we we didn't know what the
original space of Kats
was we didn't know what the original
well if you what we're deducing is the
properties of that space okay that's
what we're doing we didn't know what the
original space it's not the space that
you usually take with in right Elric qu
no no this is something new so this SP
space you're going to tell us what the
space is oh it is the space of these
integers that's
it for a particle of spin
M the space is the the the basis vectors
are you you specify what a state is by
saying what its basis vectors are its
basis vectors are simply labeled with
the values of M along this axis that's
it that's that's uh yeah if you took the
absolute value of L that Vector is that
is that an observable quantity and would
you get it is it is so let's uh let's uh
all right so let me tell you what's
[Music]
true
okay instead of the absolute value let's
take the sums of the squares of
components and see what we can find out
about that going try to do it without my
notes uh yeah let's take l
s you might think that l s is just m Max
squ that would that would make sense
right you you you take the spin and you
point it directly upward the problem
with that is that you can't know the Z
component and the X and Y component
simultaneously so if you know the the Z
component is vertically Upward at M Max
there's bound to be some uncertainty in
the X and Y
components all right so that uncertainty
in the X and Y component will tell you
that lx2 + L Y2 plus lz2 will not quite
be M Max squar right you'll have a
little extra so let's compute it that's
that's a fun thing to
compute let see I was going to go
without my notes but there's always one
thing which I have to go through to
remember yeah okay let's take L2 L2
means lx2 + L y^2 plus LZ 2 and of
course the name of the game here is to
rewrite things in terms of L plus L
minus and
LZ l+ L minus and LZ
uh
uh so what is l s let's start with L all
right so what would we do to get l s we
would add lz2 and that would be it right
classically but not quite true Quantum
mechanically because this is extra
commutator term the extra commutator
term uh L plus L minus is not equal
exactly to lx2 + L y^2 it's in fact lx2
+ L y^
2 plus a term coming from the commutator
of LX with or of LX with l y so let me
write down what that extra term is
what's the commutator of LX with l
y it's got to do with LZ there's an i
over here but the commutator also has an
i in it so the I are going to cancel and
if you work it out you find out that
it's just plus L uh that that uh L let's
see that that L Plus plus L minus is lx2
+ L y^
2 uh I think it's -
LZ and that means that l s has another
term in it which is just plus
LZ it's definitely plus over here I
think it's minus yeah just an extra term
coming from that commut the little
mistake we made when we said that L that
L plus * l minus is lx2 + L
y^2 we made a little mistake and a
little mistake is proportional to
LZ and here's how it comes in okay now
let's take L2 and operate on a state
which is M
Max which has the maximum IG value of M
what do we get l^2 on that is equal to
lus
l+ on M
Max
Plus what do I get when when LZ hits M
Max M M M Max so here we get plus n
Max SAR + n
Max times the C Vector M
Max
well what about this I I went to all
this effort but I'm still left with
something I don't know what it is zero
Zer but I do know what it is because l+
when it hits M Max has nowhere to
go all right we reached the ceiling this
is
zero so what do we found out we found
out that the I value of l
s for this state up here is just m Max S
Plus M Max
in other
words M
Max time M Max +
1 M Max * m Max +
1 not M Max s m Max * m ma 2 + 1
classically it would just be M Max squ
the maximum value but because of the
fluctuation because of the certainty
principle which says that things which
don't commute can't simultaneously be
specified there's got to be some
fluctuation in them and that fluctuation
manifests Itself by a little shift here
okay so let's take the case for example
of a spin zero particle what is l s for
a spin zero particle W that's not
interesting n Max is zero in that case
is is zero good what about a spin one
particle
turns out to be
two what about a spin a half particle a
halftimes 3 halfes is 3/4 so for a
spin what about a spin thousand
particle well yeah that's right if if MX
is big enough this little shift is not
important you know we take a spin of 100
billion billion billion we're just going
to get the square of it plus a tiny uh
irrelevant little uh change so
classically it's a very good
approximation that l s is just m Max now
if you worked out you can do this you
can work out L2 on each one of these
states and you'll get the same value all
of these states have the same value of l
s that is the quantum mechanical analog
of the statement that when you rotate
particle to change its Z component of
angular momentum it just doesn't change
the square of it it doesn't change the
magnitude of it so that's a little
exercise you could uh work
out using again just the commutation
relations of the angular momentum can
you know the square of the angular
momentum and the Z component
simultaneously yes you can and you can
check that by Computing the commutator
of
L2 with the individual components of the
angular momentum what you'll find is a
commutator of l s with any one of the
components is equal to
zero so that means although you cannot
know two components of the angular
momentum
simultaneously you can know a component
and the total squared value of the
angular
momentum every electron
has a squared spin the spin angular
momentum equal to
3/4 every electron has the same
value and it doesn't matter which
playway the electron is
oriented did you say the the spin one l
s is going to be zero for all or just
for the zero case I understand no L2 is
zero for the spin zero case Okay spin
zero only has one state it's got angular
z l is 2 I think 1 * 1 + 1 right and for
spin three what is it uh L * L + 1
is 3 * 4
12 you said that uh I'm I'm trying to
see how it's always the same no matter
which level you oh that you have to work
out so how do you work it out you you
work it out by saying let me take M
Max and now hit it with L
minus this gives me MX this gives me the
next one down Max
one and then hit it with l
s and use the tricks use the algebraic
trick tricks and show that when you hit
it with L2 it just gives you the same
iate value
the same
as
uh that all right so the algebraic
statement is that L2 on the thing in the
red box again grow a red box around the
vector that they
yday that this is
equal this is uh this is equal
to n
Max * n M Max +
1 M
Max not M Max M
Max Max M Max +
1 times the thing in the red
box all right the l^2 has exactly the
same igen value as it had for M Max
itself yeah and you get that from the
form over there you get that from
manipulating The
Operators you get that from manipulating
The Operators you use yeah you use this
formula
here and manipulate it and Fiddle around
with it and
um yeah it takes it takes a few minutes
of work
okay it also follows from the fact that
l s commutes with l+ and L
minus
it commutes with all the components of
the angular momentum so it comput
commutes with L plus and L minus and it
just follows from that so yeah they all
have the same squared
angular all right let's talk about uh
rotational invariance not in detail I'm
not going to talk about it in detail
that'll be for another
time uh but we seem to have nothing but
some discrete states of angular momentum
along the z-axis
what about rotating that uh if we
rotated it wouldn't we get angular
momento which had fractional value along
the z-axis and maybe some components in
the other direction so for that let's
let's concentrate for Simplicity on the
spinner half case on the spinner half
case the spinner half
particle the spin angular momentum has
only two states it's not true that an
electron has only two states
uh it has an orbital motion and it has a
spin angular momentum let's just
concentrate on the spin and nothing else
then concentrating on the spin there's
only two possibilities up and down half
spin up half spin down let's call them I
don't like using red for
equations let's call
them up plus and down
minus these are the two basis States for
the spin angular momentum along the
z-axis but there are certainly many more
states that I can write down these are
not the only States I can write in fact
the general Quantum state of a system
with
two states like this is to add them with
complex
numbers Alpha and beta are complex
numbers what is the probability in such
a state that the spin is up Al squ Alpha
star
Alpha okay
probability for
up equals Alpha star
Alpha and the probability for down is
equal to Beta star
beta we add them together total
probability has to be one and so one of
the rules is Alpha star Alpha plus beta
star
beta =
1 one other
fact that if I were to make a phase
rotation of each of these complex
numbers in other words if I was to
multiply Alpha and beta by the same
phase e to the I Theta e to the I Theta
that does not change the physical
character of the state and the reason is
because all interesting
quantities
are things times complex
conjugates these will cancel out of any
interesting physical quantity and so
there's one well the way to say it is
there's
one degree of Freedom namely the overall
phase of Alpha and beta which is
unphysical and which doesn't matter
which is
irrelevant okay let's count now the
number of variables the number of
parameters that it takes to specify a
Quantum state of an of spin of an
electron Alpha is a complex number it
has two real
components beta is a complex number it
has two real components so so far we
have four real
components but we have a constraint
Alpha star Alpha plus beta star beta is
1 so that means only three real
components number of independent uh
variables on the other hand one
combination the overall phase is
unphysical let's just IGN Let's uh
eliminate it some one way or another
that brings us down to only two
independent variables specifying a
Quantum
State okay two independent variables
specify the quantum State now how many
independent variables if an electri
or a little arrow of a given
length it's angular momentum Vector how
many variables does it take to specify
the orientation of that angular momentum
two polar and asmal
angle uh of the
sphere describing the end of the vector
they're the same thing you rotate around
the spin of the um electron by varying
Alpha and beta but no matter which axis
you measure the angular momentum it's
always an
integer that is to say the actual
measured value is an integer what about
the average value can the average value
be not I'm sorry it's not an integer
it's a half integer plus a half or minus
a half can you get anything but plus a
half or minus a half for the average
value the average values
so what does the average value mean what
does the average value mean the average
value means you take repeated identical
experiments where in each experiment the
electron was prepared with exactly the
same Quantum State and in each case you
measure the Z component of the angular
momentum sometimes you get plus a half
sometimes you get minus a half the
average is to take the Ensemble of all
of them together addir up the Z
component of angular momentum divide by
the number of uh experiments that you
did just the average angular momentum
that can certainly be anything that does
not have to be uh for example if we just
chose alpha = 1 and betaal 1 what's the
average Z component of the angular
momentum zero
zero in fact this happens to correspond
to the spin of the electron along the x
axis instead of along the
z-axis up along on the x-axis it's been
rotated by
90° nevertheless when you mult when you
measure it along the z-axis you'll get
plus or minus one but the average is
zero so it's the averages which behave
like the classical variables if you take
a spin up and you rotate it by
90° the average spin along that vertical
axis will be zero the averages which
behave
classically uh this is a spin along the
x-axis what's a spin along the Y AIS
anybody
remember no no no no no okay good good
it's a good guess but it's the wrong
guess this is a spin all right this is
the z-axis here's the z-axis here's the
x-axis this corresponds to a spin which
is pointing along the x-axis in this
Direction with a plus
sign with a minus sign
it corresponds to a spin pointing still
along the x-axis but in the opposite
direction we still haven't found the one
which points along the Y
[Applause]
[Music]
AIS I and minus I correspond to
orientation along the Y
AIS and with other values of Alpha and
beta you can make spins which are
pointing along an arbitrary axis
pointing along an arbitrary axis means
if you measure the component along that
axis you'll always get the same
answer
so
[Applause]
uh that's pretty much spin in a
nutshell and as I said it is the the
electric charge the mass the spin of a
particle are its most important
properties
now there's a correlation which I should
not only mention but emphasize very
strongly because it's one of the Prime
facts of elementary particle physics
it's actually a theorem of relativistic
quantum mechanics but we're not going to
try to prove
it and the theorem is a correlation
between the values of the spin of the
particle and whether it's a fon or a
boson remember fans are the ones that
you can't put two of them in the same
state bans they have a poly Exclusion
Principle Bans are the ones that you can
put into the same state they behave like
photons and they make classical
waves half spin particles are always
ferons without Exception by half spin I
now mean 1/2 three Hales 5 Hales
anything which is an a um measur in half
units know
uh where the spectrum is half units
instead of units those are all
Fons and all particles which have
integer Spectrum like this are bons spin
zero particle is always a bon without
exception a spin uh two particle is
always a
bosone what happens if you take two half
spin
particles take to half spin
particles uh which one of which happens
to have have one value of M and the
other has another value of M each one
having a half unit it could be 3es and-
7es or whatever what happens if you add
up their angular
momentum whole you get an integer not a
half integer right that tells you that
objects which are made up out of an even
number of fans are always
bons any object made of an even number
of Fons will have an integer
spin because it has an integer spin it's
a
bon uh what happens if you take a bon
and add it to a
firon oh let me give an example an
example would be a hydrogen atom a
proton is a half spin particle just like
an electron half not three halves not
five halves a half proton has a half
spin just like the electron you take a
hydrogen Peron you take an electron and
you put it in orbit and you create a
hydrogen atom the hydrogen atom becomes
a bon now this is not the this is not
the hydrogen isotope this is the
hydrogen atom with just a single proton
in its
nucleus
um deuteron is a proton bound to a
neutron Neutron also is a half spin
particle a deuteron is a bon half Spin
and another half spin
what about
duum duum is a proton and a neutron that
forms a nucleus with a electron in orbit
around
it okay what's the what are the quantum
what are the uh the possible values of
the Z component to spin going to be you
take it's it's basically three half
integers added up three half integers
will always be a half integer again okay
so a bon together with a fon is a fon a
bon together with a bon is a bon and a
firon together with a fion is a both
okay so theum is a
fon uh
hydrogen with only one proton what did I
say duum is yeah hydrogen is a bon I
think I got it
right incidentally particles in an
particles always have the same spin same
mass opposite
charge uh what about positronium
positronium is a positron and orbit
around that well electron and a positron
orbiting each other what would that
be bons have the property of being able
to go through things or I heard bons
have the property the what uh be in the
same state I I heard like super
conductivity is like two pairs of
electrons together and they act like a
bon therefore that it's sort of
transparent or something like that well
okay before you can understand the
superconductor you have to understand a
super fluid a super fluid for example
helium forms a super fluid let's talk
about helium what the is helium a boson
or Fon ordinary
helium okay why is
that even numbers of nucleons and electr
two protons two neutrons and two
electrons two protons and two neutrons
makes a helium nucleus an alpha particle
and two electrons it's a
boson uh so whatever bosons are helium
is a good example of them helium atoms
can all go into the same
state and it's when basically a super a
super fluid of helium atoms is almost
like a classical wave that you make by
piling them up all in the same state
that's not quite right but it's close
enough for us um they all move
together uh in the same
state now an
electron and metal is a
firmon you can't put two electrons into
the same state but how about pairs of
electrons here here's a paradox okay
here's a
paradox uh which we talked about last
night but talk about it again tonight
you take two Fons and you put them
together and make a B on okay how can it
be that you can put two of those
composits into the same state when you
couldn't put the constituents into the
same state does that make
sense so does it or doesn't it no no
okay I'll tell you it does make sense
I'll tell you what what exactly it
means
um you know let's do that next time I
think I'm I'm running I'm running in a
sche um and remind me remind me about
this is so interesting that it's worth
uh 10 minutes on how two firion when
they make a bon how you can put the
bosons into the same state even though
the firion can't be put into the same
state okay so we should get back to that
I'm reaching that point in the evening
where I I'll get confused if I try
it yeah since uh protons and neutrons
are composite why is it that they're
half spin is it the spin Composites of
odd numbers of Fons proton is three
quarks a quark is a half spin particle
okay so it's it's going to be a firon
three firion make a firon all right just
the last observation has to do with the
PO Exclusion
Principle all comes it was all
discovered from staring at the uh
periodic table long
enough um howy said that you can't put
more than one electron into the same or
orbital in an
atom no he didn't say that he said you
can't put more than one electron into
the same Quantum State he knew very well
that you can put two and no more than
two electrons in the same orbital state
in the atom he knew that because he
knew roughly speaking that that if you
take a hydrogen atom you double the
charge of the nucleus and you put
another electron in the two electrons go
into the same state the same orbital
St so Po's Exclusion Principle did not
apply to the orbital motion applies to
the entire Quantum
State the entire Quantum State includes
the spin State you can put two electrons
into the same orbital in an atom as long
as the spins are in the opposite
direction you can't put two electrons
with spin in the same direction as long
as the axis here you can't put them in
the same direction but you can put them
into spin states in the opposite
direction as long as they are different
as long as they are different two
electrons and that's the property ofon
two of them can't be in the same Quantum
state but Quantum State includes
everything about the
particle so that means in every orbital
in an atom you can put no more than two
electrons and when there are two
electrons they have to be in uh what's
called spin singlets which mean the
spins cancel you can think of that like
mesh gears right if they're going in the
same
rotation they go in opposite directions
right yeah they're going in the same
direction you just the gears
indeed I know I've done that in my
car orbital More Than Just sh
in what's theal orbital mean the state
of an
electron if you ignore the
spin orbit or uh am I using orbital in a
way that a chemist wouldn't use it who's
a chemist yes I
am okay I'm what I mean by orbital
motion is not what a chemist means by an
orbital what's an orbital again that's
some spdf yeah uh I mean a Quantum State
a solution of a shinger equation a
solution of the shringer equation
ignoring spin it creates the the the
chart the Periodic Chart that's up there
and so that's how come you
have uh two electrons in the you have
two things you have SPD and all that
stuff has to do with orbital angular
momentum but then this principal quantum
number which is called in and when I
speak about the orbital motion I mean
both in and the orbital angular momentum
that's a chemist to call orbital SPD and
all that stuff you know what that stands
for I don't know what that stands
for yeah it does mean it does mean
sperical but it actually means a Quantum
state of zero angular
momentum p means angular momentum one
this is the orbital motion of there D is
angular momentum 2 f is angular momentum
three and I don't what G comes after F I
don't remember but
uh uh all right that's the uh that's the
orbital angular momentum of the electron
but the other quantum number is the
distance basically the distance of the
electron from the uh from the proton and
that's the principal quantum number so
what I would call the orbital motion
meaning this the actual motion of the
electron is a composite of principal
quantum number and the orbital quantum
number call that let's just call that a
state of orbital motion the state of or
in uh both principle and uh all right so
the rule is that poy devised was that no
electron can have all of its quantum
numbers the
same okay
that's incidentally the orbital well
yeah
okay from what you're saying can you
deduce how many electrons can each shell
in an yeah how many it can be not how
many are you reduce the maximum number
yeah yeah
um
yeah we're not going to do that now
uh see I Haven intended to do it at
all so you got the principal quantum
number then the orbital quantum number
and then the
spin let's take let's talk about
orbitals in the sense that chemists use
it orbital means SPD in okay
um an S an S particle is spin zero that
means the orbital angular momentum is
zero and there's only one or one state
of the orbital angular momentum what
about p p is angular momentum one we're
talking about orbital angular momentum
one but the rules of angular momentum
are the same for orbital angular
momentum spin angular momentum so if the
orbital angular momentum is one that
means there's three
possibilities if the orbital angular
momentum is two that's a d-wave or
D State there are five
states So when you say one that that
actually means up and down everything
everything being specified two electrons
all the things which all the things
which can be simultaneously specified
specified and then when there's three
then there's two in each of those three
so you get six more electrons or a total
of eight right
exactly uh I hadn't intended to talk
about Atomic physics today
can it's extremely
interesting and some features of atomic
physics show up again when you're
thinking about quirks orbiting uh each
other and so
forth a little different okay um any
questions and if not
uh I have a date tonight Friday
night have a date with my pillow
for more please visit us at stanford.edu